# XIAOJIAN XU

[Homepage] [Google Scholar] [Github] [Twitter] [Linkedin]

Department of Computer Science and Engineering & Washington University in St. Louis

### About me

#### Current research

My current research pursues to combine computational imaging, optimization, and machine learning to
enable new intelligent imaging technology for various imaging applications including denoising, deblurring,
super-resolution, image segmentation, optical microscopy, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), radar, and autonomous driving, etc. My research efforts are taking place at two complementary levels: (a) the fundamental
and mathematical aspects of imaging; (b) application-oriented projects in collaboration with researchers in
medicine, biology, and computer vision.

#### Research interests

Computational Imaging, Optimization, Deep Learning, Inverse Problems, Computer Vision, Signal Processing

#### EDUCATION

Washington University in St. Louis (WUSTL), St. Louis, MO, USA 9/2017-6/2022 (expected)

Ph.D student in Computer Science (GPA: 3.87/4.00), advised by Dr. Ulugbek Kamilov

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China 9/2014-6/2017

M.Eng in Communication & Information Engineering (Graduated with Honors)

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China 9/2010-6/2014

• B.Eng in Communication Engineering (GPA: 3.89/4.00)

#### Working Experience

#### Facebook Reality Labs Research (FRLR)

5/2021-8/2021

Research intern with Dr. Brian Wheelwright

Seattle (remote)

• Built the ray-tracing model for peripheral display system in Oculus, solved its display calibration problem, and designed an efficient camera-to-display mapping for its real-time rendering using neural representation.

#### Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL)

5/2019-8/2019

Research intern with Dr. Hassan Mansour

Boston

 Investigated in 3D tomographic imaging problems and solved the problem by proposing two distinct methods, model-based optimization and data driven deep learning.

### AWARDS & HONORS

Honors	
<ul> <li>Honored Ph.D student in Computer Science &amp; Engineering department</li> </ul>	2021
Outstanding Graduate Student	2017
Scholarship	
Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship	2016
Graduate Student Second-Rank Academic Scholarship	2015
Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship	2014
National Inspirational Scholarship	2013
People's First-Rank Scholarship	2012
National Inspirational Scholarship	2011
Others	
• Third-prize of 'Internet+' Entrepreneurship Competition in Sichuan Province	2016

Great Award of Intelligent City Technology Competition

2016

Award of Hackathon Programming Competition

2015 2011

Second Prize of Electronic Design Competition in UESTC

## SKILLS

- Languages: Python, Matlab, C, Java
- Skills: Optimization, Inverse problems, Tensorflow, Pytorch, Deep learning, Linux, TCP/IP

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### Model-based deep learning for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

• Developed imaging-model-assisted learning methods such as unsupervised learning, self-supervised and unrolling framework for different imaging tasks with various noise corruption challenges ([1, 2, 6, 7, 9]).

#### Learning-based optimization for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

Extensively investigated in variants of Plug-and-Play priors (PnP) and Regularized by denoising (RED) approaches for various imaging tasks by combining the imaging models with the deep-learning priors, in both theory and practice ([3, 4, 5]).

### Compressed and stochastic algorithms for large-scale imaging

7/2018 - Present

• Investigated in large-scale imaging problems by developing stochastic variants of optimization- and learning-based algorithms with convergence guarantee ([6, 7, 10]).

### Some earlier research experience

3/2014 - 6/2017

- Intelligent home system design and development.
- Routing and resource scheduling algorithms for large-scale network software defined networks (SDN).

#### Publications

#### **Preprints**

- [1] **X. Xu** et al., "Learning-based Motion Artifact Removal Networks (LEARN) for Quantitative  $R_2^*$  Mapping," arXiv:2109.01622 [eess], Sep. 2021, [Online]. Available: http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.01622
- [2] S. Kahali, S. V. V. N. Kothapalli, **X. Xu**, U. S. Kamilov, and D. A. Yablonskiy, "Deep-Learning-Based Accelerated and Noise-Suppressed Estimation (DANSE) of quantitative Gradient Recalled Echo (qGRE) MRI metrics associated with Human Brain Neuronal Structure and Hemodynamic Properties," bioRxiv, 2021, doi: 10.1101/2021.09.10.459810.

#### **Published**

(\* indicates equal contribution)

- [3] X. Xu, Y. Sun, J. Liu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Provable convergence of plug-and-play priors with MMSE denoisers," IEEE Signal Process. Lett., vol. 27, pp. 1280–1284, 2020.
- [4] X. Xu, J. Liu, Y. Sun, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Boosting the performance of plug-and-play priors via denoiser scaling," in 54th Asilomar Conf. on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2020, pp. 1305–1312.
- [5] X. Xu\*, Y. Sun\*, Z. Wu\*, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Scalable Plug-and-Play ADMM With Convergence Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 849–863, 2021.
- [6] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "SGD-Net: Efficient Model-Based Deep Learning With Theoretical Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 598–610, 2021.
- [7] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Stochastic Deep Unfolding for Imaging Inverse Problems," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2021, pp. 1395–1399.
- [8] X. Xu, O. Dhifallah, H. Mansour, P. T. Boufounos, and P. V. Orlik, "Robust 3D Tomographic Imaging of the lonospheric Electron Density," in 2020 IEEE Int. Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), 2020, pp. 437–440.

[9] J. Liu, Y. Sun, X. Xu, and U. S. Kamilov, "Image restoration using total variation regularized deep image prior," in 2019 IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2019, pp. 7715–7719.

[10] X. Xu and U. S. Kamilov, "SignProx: One-bit proximal algorithm for nonconvex stochastic optimization," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), Brighton, UK, May 2019, pp. 7800–7804.

### INVITED TALKS

- SIAM Conference on Imaging Science, 07/2020
- UCLouvain, Image and Signal Processing Group Seminar, 09/2020
- Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 10/2021

### Professional Services

- Conferences reviewer: ISBI, ICASSP
- Journals reviewer: IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), IEEE Transactions on Computational Imaging (TCI), Optics Communications, Scientific Reports

### TEACHING & SUPERVISION EXPERIENCE

### (Head) TA for Optimization

2019-2020

Assistant Instructor

St. Louis

Served as head assistant instructor and guest lecturer for course "Optimization" and "Large-Scale Optimization for Data Science" and obtained high evaluation from students.

#### Students supervision

7/2018-Present

Research Supervisor

St. Louis

#### **Current students**

- Eddie Chandler, "Inhomogeneity correction for MRI", now B.S. student at WUSTL
- Yixuan Luo, "Deep-learning-based image segmentation", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Michael Kincheloe, "Reinforcement learning for MRI artifacts correction". now B.S. student at WUSTL Previous students
- \* Zhixin Sun, "Neural representation for MRI reconstruction", coming Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Weijie Gan, "Fast MRI reconstruction and artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Jiarui Xing, "Deep-learning-based MRI artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at University of Virginia
- Shiqi Xu, "Sparse Fourier ptychographic microscopy", now Ph.D student at Duke University
- Hao Tang, "Adversarially robust classifiers for image reconstruction", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Ryogo Suzuki, "Unfolding networks for image restoration", now at Rakuten Group, Inc.
- Yukun Li, "Single image denoising", now at Baidu Inc.
- Fa Long, "Dictionary learning for image restoration", now at Tencent Inc.